Guide to the Sylvia Boehm Acker Papers ALBA.202
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sylvia Boehm Acker Papers
1937-1981
1937-1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Acker, Sylvia Boehm.
ALBA.202
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
George Boehm joined the International Brigades as a volunteer in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in February 1937, and was killed during the Battle of the Ebro in July or August 1938. The collection was donated by Boehm's widow, Sylvia Diner Boehm Acker, who later married Leon Acker, an International Brigades volunteer from Poland. The collection includes Boehm's letters to Silvia from Spain, memorabilia, clippings, and material relating to Sylvia's lifelong activity with International Brigades veterans' and refugee aid organizations.
Provenance
The Sylvia Boehm Acker Collection was donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in 1981 by Sylvia Acker. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
George Boehm was born in Velika Pisanica, Croatia on November 5, 1897. He sailed to Europe from New York City to volunteer in the International Brigades in Spain in February 1937. An artist, Spanish teacher, and interpreter, Boehm was killed during the Battle of the Ebro in July or August 1938. Boehm's wife, Sylvia Diner Boehm, participated in fundraising and support work for the International Briagdes volunteers in New York City. After George Boehm's death, Sylvia married another Spanish Civil War veteran, Leon Acker, who had served with the Jewish battalion of the Dombrowski Brigade of Polish volunteers. In the decades after the war, Sylvia remained active in committees to aid Spanish Refugees and Spanish Civil War veterans.
Scope and Content Note
A substantial portion of the collection consists of George Boehm's letters from Spain to his wife, Sylvia, with notes written by her on the envelopes. Also included are letters to Sylvia from the Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade regarding her efforts to learn about George's fate in Spain; clippings about the Spanish Civil War, Spanish refugees, and politics; original artwork and paste-up of a flyer for a dinner-dance sponsored by the Botvin Committee to Aid Jewish Volunteers in Spain (in Yiddish); and an autograph of Dolores Ibárruri.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are organized in one series:
Missing Title
I, Subject Files, 1937-1981.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs and posters from the Sylvia Boehm Acker Collection have been transferred to the Non-Print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library.
Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, Polish.; Articles.; Speeches.; Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Clippings (information artifacts); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Botvin Committee to Aid Jewish Volunteers in Spain; Ibárruri, Dolores, 1895-1989; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Acker, Leon.; Acker, Sylvia Boehm.; Boehm, George, 1897-1938; Casa, Enrique Carlos de la
- Series I: Subject Files, 1937-1981.
  - Acker, Leon: Military document; letter of introduction to United Electrical Workers, Local 1224, 1938, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Acker, Sylvia: Receipts for Spanish Aid Contributions (Medical Bureau and Polski Comitet Solidarnosci z Ludem Hiszpani), 1939, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ante el Pleno de Nuestro Comitó Central (annotated pamphlet), Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boehm, George: Death certificate; notes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Botvin Committee to Aid Jewish Volunteers of Spain, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, undated, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade to Sylvia Boehm, Jul 1937-Dec 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: George Boehm (Letters to Mrs. Belche Camel, Mrs. Tillie Diner, and draft of telegram to Governor of Alabama re: Clarence Norris execution, with notes by Sylvia Boehm on envelopes), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: George Boehm to Sylvia Boehm, undated, Feb 1937-Jul 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: George Boehm to Sylvia Boehm, Aug 1937-Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: George Boehm to Sylvia Boehm, Jan 1938-Jul 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Joe Gibbons to Sylvia Boehm, Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Sylvia Boehm Acker (letter from Fruma Bogen-Dua of Watsaw, in Yiddish, 1964; letter to Miriam Tache re: visit to IB veteran Ickovic Salaman in Czechoslovakia, 1967; reply from Miriam Tache), Jul 1964, Sep 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ibarruri, Dolores: Autograph, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Periodicals: News Bulletin of the International Brigades (mimeographed, pp. 3 and 4 missing, and odd pages); Our Fight - Journal of the XV International Brigade (3 issues); Acero, Organo del V Cuerpo de Ejercito; Mackenzie Papineau Daily (typed, 2 unrelated pages), Aug 1937-Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pins, medals and commemorative object [Separated to ALBA Artifacts. Consult archivist.] One pin "Honor Guest", with ribbon, Hippodrome Benefit, June 28, 1937, is in this folder., undated, 1937-1939, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Spanish Civil War Prisoner, Refugee, and International Brigades Aid Appeals (including a postcard with photo from a french refugee camp, and a printed invitation from Dashiell Hammett to a benefit reception and exhibition honring William Gropper), undated, 1941, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Spanish Refugees: "Proceedings, National Emergency Conference on an Immediate Program to Aid Spanish Refugees" (Hotel Hamilton, Washington DC), Mar 15, 1941-Mar 16, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Speech delivered by Dr. Enrique Carlos de la Casa, Jul 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Reunions and anniversaries, 1967, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)